Guide to the Walter G. Vincenti papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Walter G. Vincenti papers
1917-2007
SC1022
Vincenti, Walter G., (Walter Guido), 1917-
14 Linear feet
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Materials were the gift of Walter G. Vincenti, 2004.
Information about Access
Access: Materials are open for research use.
Biographical/Historical note
Walter G. Vincenti earned his AB in engineering at Stanford in 1938 and his Engineer’s degree in mechanical engineering in 1940. He was a research scientist with the National Advisory Committee for Aeronautics (NACA), working at the Ames Aeronautical Laboratory at Moffett Field until he joined the Stanford faculty in 1957. He cofounded Stanford’s Program in Values, Technology, and Science in 1971 and served several terms as its chair.
Scope and Contents note
Collection contains Vincenti’s lectures from a class on the history of the industrial revolution taught at Stanford’s overseas campus in Cliveden, undated; class materials and lectures from VTS 121 Technology in Society: Historical Perspective, 1981; lectures by Claude B. Fohlen on the Industrial Revolution 1972; lectures by Paul A. David on technology, society, and economy 1971; letters from Harriet Jones with photocopied papers of aeronautical scientist R. T. Jones, 1999-2000; and a seminar on fluid mechanics.
Access Terms
David, Paul A.; Fohlen, Claude B.; Jones, Robert T. (Robert Thomas), 1910-; Stanford University -- General subdivision--Curricula.;; Industrial revolution.; Technology--Social aspects.
Collection Contents
- Class materials and miscellaneous papers, 1971-2000; Accession ARCH-2005-156; 0.5 Linear feet
  - Cliveden lectures [history of the industrial revolution], manuscript text (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - VTS 121 Technology in Society: Historical Perspective - class information, lecture schedule, etc., 1981 Autumn (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - VTS 121 Technology in Society: Historical Perspective - lectures, manuscript text (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - VTS 121 Technology in Society: Historical Perspective - lectures, manuscript text (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Fohlen, Claude B., lectures on the Industrial Revolution, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - David, Paul A., lectures on technology, society, and economy, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - VTS 3 class lecture outline, 1980 Oct (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letter from Harriet Jones with photocopied papers of R. T. Jones, 1999 Mar (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letter from Harriet Jones with color photocopies of "The Shaping of Wings to Minimize the Formation of Shock Waves" by R. T. Jones (1945) and other materials, 1999 Oct (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letter from Harriet Jones with photocopied papers of R. T. Jones and photograph of his first wife Hazel St. Clair Jones, 2000 June (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Additional materials, 1917-1997; Accession ARCH-2008-190
  - The Screw Propeller, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Transactions of the Society of Naval Architects, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Control-Volume Analysis Materials and early versions, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - NASM Search Committee, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - The Davis Wing and the Problem of Airfoil Design - Penultimate Draft, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Davis Wing, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Flush Riveting 66970, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Flush Riveting Ms., undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Durand-Lesley Paper Figure Originals, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Control-Volume Analysis Drafts, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Loose Correspondence/Papers, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Status Report and Development Plans: Program in Values, Technology, and Society, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Unlabeled Binder (Britain in the Industrial Revolution), 1979 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Ombudsman, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Durand-Lesley Tests - Miscellaneous Notes, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Durand-Lesley Tests - ASME Paper, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Durand-Lesley Tests - Notes on References, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Durand-Lesley Tests - Draft Manuscript, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Britannia Br.--Corresp., 1977 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Britannia Bridge - Notes, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Durand-Lesley Tests - Revised Draft, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Loose Papers/Articles About Vicenti, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Selected Papers of William Frederick Durand, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - The Davis Wing Drafts, 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Hansen, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Govt. Agencies, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Aerodynamics, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Patents, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Innovation, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Strength, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Production, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Outline, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Ideas, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Misc., undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Control-Volume Analysis, 1977-1979 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Seminar on Davis Wing, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Inclined Plate at M=1 - Flow Over Top Surface, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Nonlinear Conical Flow - Miscellaneous Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Leading-Edge Suction on NACA 64A010, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Transonic Wind Tunnels, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - 6'x6' Supersonic Tunnel, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Finite-Span Pressure Distribution Tests, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Miscelleanous Stuff from Newman Fisher, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Flow Near M=Infinity, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Aerodynamic Noise, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Numerical Work for TN3499, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Potential of Non-Lifting Triangular Wing and evaluation of (integral), undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - First-Order Wave Structure, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Suppliers, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence between Brookins and Arnold, 1917-1938 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - T&C Committee, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - VPI Visit, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - American Heritage, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - A&S Productions, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - SSofS Note, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - SHOT Session, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Personal Stuff, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Non-Euclidean Geometry, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - National Advisory Committee for Aeronautics Technical Notes, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Unlabeled Documents, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Triangular Flat Plate at M=1, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous Transonic Results, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Wedge with Detached Shock-Method of Solution, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Finite-Span Wedges Near Shock Attachment, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Exp. Study of Detached Waves - 8x8 inch Tunnel, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Home Maps, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - AA 210A, 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - AA 210A, 1969-1970 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - AA 210A, 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - AA 210A, 1967-1968 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - AA 210A, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - AA 210A, 1965-1966 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - AA 210A, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - AA 210A, 1961-1962 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - AA 210A, 1960-1961 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - AA 210A, 1959-1960 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - AA 210A, 1958-1959 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Problem Stencils, 1957-1958 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - AA 211A, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - AA 211B, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - AA 215, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Loose Graph Paper, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Talk for Stanford-Lockhead Meeting on Radiation Coupled Flows, undated (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Seminar Talk at Ohio State and Mich., 1969 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Durand-Lesley Tests - National Archive Material, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Personal, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Personal Photos, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - VTSS, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Administration, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Budget, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - VTS Funding, 1979-1982 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Personnel, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - VTS Correspondence, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Talks, 1979-1981 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Curriculum, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Courses, 1981-1982 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Announcements, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Other Courses and Programs, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Evalutation, 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - VTS Miscellaneous, 1981-1983 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - ET Course Reports, undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - ET Tabulated Data, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - ET Misc. Reports, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Research Prospects, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Individually Designed Majors, 1981, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Western Culture Course, 1979-1982 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - SHOT Advisory Council, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - NASA History Communication, 1978-1986 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Islamic Project, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - National Academy of Engineering, 1978, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - AIAA Fellow Review, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Miscellaneous, 1984, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Academy of Astronautics, 1970, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Society for Scientific Exploration, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Technology Seminar, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - SHOT Awards, 1985-1987 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - "Albatrosses", 1983-1985 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Physical Gas Dynamics, 1965, 1966, 1974, 1976, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Alumni Seminar in Britain, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Sabbatical, 1970-1971, 1982-1983 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Retirement, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Recommendations, 1981-1997 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Referee Reports, 1970-1973, 1973-1979,1983 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Guggenheim Fellowship, 1962-1965 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Ph.D. Exams, 1965-1973 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Travel, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Britannia Bridge--Reviews, 1979, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - "Otway O'Mira Pardee", undated (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Annual Review Vol. 6, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - VTS 121, Autumn 1973 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - VTS 121, Winter 1973 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - VTS 113 (History), 1972 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Class roll books (VTSS 2, VTS 122, VTS 2, VTS 121, Hum 113), 1979-1987 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Status Report and Development Plans: Program in Values, Technology, and Society, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - A.E. 210c, Spring 1959 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - A.E. 211a, Winter 1960 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Physical Gas Dynamics Revisions, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - A.A. 215, Winter 1970 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - F44620-69-C-0006, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1993-2002 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - NSF GK-30635, 1971-1974 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - A.A. 210a, Autumn 1967 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - A.A. 210a, Autumn 1971 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - A.E. 210b, Winter 1959 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Misc., circa 1952 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Paul David's Course, Spring 1979 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Possible Topics after Book, 1983-1986 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Assorted Printouts, undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - JW Swan and the Invention of the Incandescent Electric Lamp, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - A Symposium in Honor of Milton Van Dyke, 1997 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence regarding "What Engineers Know", 1983-1993 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Unlabeled Slides, undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Reshoots-Vicenti, circa 1991 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Loose Version of "What Engineers Know", 1990 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Western Culture and Technology: The Ancient World, 1985-1986 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Unlabeled Lectures, 1980-1987 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Selected Readings - VTSS 2, 1985-1986 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - VTS 2, Spring 1980 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - VTS 2, Winter 1981 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - VTS 2, Winter 1982 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - VTS 2 - Misc. Notes, 1981-1983 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Unlabeled Diagrams, undated (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Indexes, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Bulletin of the American Physical Society, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Style Manual, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - An ASME Paper, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - "Technology, Culture, Society", 1985 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Walter Vincenti, undated (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Unlabeled Binder (Didactic Material, General Histories, etc), circa 1985 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Unlabeled Binder (Planning, Correspondence, Ideas for Text), circa 1985 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Study of Pressure Distributions, undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Various Correspondence and Notes, 1983-1986 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Raleigh Paper, 1987 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - FR-Manuscript, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - FR-Notes on Sources, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Unlabeled Binder (Technology and Culture, "After the Fact"), 1995-1997 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - VTS 3, 1998-1989 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Bureau of Aeronautics Specification, 1948 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Dynamic Stability and Control Research, 1951 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - NASA-Robert G. Gilruth, 1967 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Cornell Aeronautical Laboratory, 1951 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - The Variable Stability Airplane, 1988 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - The Weight Envelope, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous Printouts, undated (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Final Report on the Demonstration and Trials of the Sikorsky XPBS-1, 1938 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - GH-86-26, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - GH-88-1, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - CBA-18-1, 1918 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - CBA-20-1, 1920 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - CBA-25-1, 1925 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - CBA-28-2, undated (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - CBA-29-1, 1929 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Loose Photocopies of Articles, 1911-1942 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence about Engineering Knowledge, 1988 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Initial Draft - Chapter 7 The Anatomy of Engineering Design Knowledge, undated (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence and Edits, circa 1987 (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Unlabeled Photocopies, undated (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Special Study on the Records of the National Advisory Committee for Aeronautics, 19730 (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Unlabeled Folder with Photocopies, 1935 (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Unlabeled Packet of Photocopies, circa 1936 (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - AR-41 to AR46, 1941 (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - GH-84 to GH-47, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - AR 37 to AR-39, 1937 (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - Unlabeled Photocopies, undated (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - The Struggle Against the Sea, undated (Box 9, Folder 28)
  - 1990 Alumni Trip, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 29)
  - Initial Draft and Assorted Papers, 1995 (Box 9, Folder 30)
- Fluid mechanics seminar, William Frederick Durand: From Wooden Ships to Jet Engines, 2007 Apr 20; 1 optical disc(s) (DVD)